<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: React.js | Robert Mosolgo]]></title>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/categories/react-dot-js/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-08T21:56:41-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Mosolgo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why (I Think) We're Leaving Batman.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2014/09/07/why-i-think-were-leaving-batman-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-07T20:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2014/09/07/why-i-think-were-leaving-batman-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sadly, <a href="http://get.planningcenteronline.com">PCO</a> is getting out of the batman.js game.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>From where I sit, I think it boils down to:</p>

<ul>
<li>The framework never hit critical mass (and lost what it had)</li>
<li>The framework&rsquo;s magic made some problems impossible to debug</li>
<li>Client-side apps aren&rsquo;t good for business</li>
<li>Rails, Turbolinks &amp; React will do just fine</li>
</ul>


<p>Batman.js is a great framework with some amazing, well-tested features and I&rsquo;m sorry to see it go this way for us!</p>

<h2>No Critical Mass</h2>

<p>Batman.js was an early entrant to the &ldquo;Framework Wars&rdquo;. It was production-ready by early 2013, which made it appealing at that point. However,</p>

<ul>
<li>there was very little &ldquo;evangelism&rdquo; by its creators (almost no talks, very little documentation, no &ldquo;media presence&rdquo;)</li>
<li>early adopters were not &ldquo;invited in&rdquo; (unanswered github issues, for example)</li>
</ul>


<p>When Shopify pulled out (around <a href="https://github.com/batmanjs/batman/graphs/contributors">fall 2013</a>?), a ton of knowledge and resources were removed with no viable replacement.</p>

<h2>Magic Problems</h2>

<p>Batman.js is loaded with awesome APIs that were fun to use and satisfying when they worked. However, when it <em>didn&rsquo;t work</em>, you were up a creek without a paddle. There was:</p>

<ul>
<li>no helpful error messages</li>
<li>no support on github, stack overflow or IRC</li>
<li>no documentation or information of any kind about the inner workings</li>
<li>no debugging tools</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve seen a lot of batman.js users pull their hair out yelling, &ldquo;Why doesn&rsquo;t this <em>work</em>?!&rdquo; Indeed, that&rsquo;s what drove me to learn it from the source.</p>

<h2>Client-Side Issues</h2>

<p>Making a whole app in JavaScript has a lot of sex appeal, but several things make it bad for real-life business:</p>

<ul>
<li>Bug-tracking tools (namely Bugsnag for JS) are not as good (especially when you throw CoffeeScript &amp; minification in the mix)</li>
<li>Browser environments are outside your control (I got a lot of bugsnags for peoples' browser extensions)</li>
<li>State can get weird &mdash; after having the app open for an hour, data can just get messed up! (Maybe this doesn&rsquo;t happen for better programmers.)</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Not my problem:</em></p>

<p><img src="/images/extension_errors.png" width="500"></p>

<p><em>No es mi problema:</em></p>

<p><img src="/images/extension_errors2.png" width="900"></p>

<p>You just don&rsquo;t realize the luxury of reliable bugsnags until they&rsquo;re gone! So many Check-Ins bugsnags leave no trace of what actually went wrong.</p>

<h2>Other Options are OK, too</h2>

<p>We have a solid data model, HTML templates and CSS to boot. It stinks to throw away all that code, but I forgot how amazingly fast it is to code Ruby on Rails.</p>

<p>JS MVC types will look down their noses at Turbolinks, but it <em>works</em> and it has a lot of eyes on it. Combined with <code>react-rails</code>, it&rsquo;s a really strong option!</p>

<h2>What Now?</h2>

<p>In short, Rails-rendered HTML, Turbolinks &amp; <code>form_for ... remote: true</code>, and ReactJS for live-updates. There are a few things I am looking forward to:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>RUBY BUGSNAGS</strong> with stack traces, request environments and everything!</li>
<li><strong>Less state.</strong> Fewer things that can randomly affect other things in ways I didn&rsquo;t think about.</li>
<li><strong>ReactJS.</strong> <code>Batman.View</code> is an amazing thing, but it makes me appreciate the dead-simple API of a React component. It can only get data from one place, no other objects can mess with it, its lifecycle is <em>very</em> simple (and works as documented), etc etc. I write a lot more code to do a lot less with React, but I think it&rsquo;s going to be a lot more stable, and that&rsquo;s worth it.</li>
</ul>


<p>We held on to Batman.js for a long time because it lended itself to <em>live-updating everything</em>. I think React is going to cover the a few key things there, and just <em>changing pages</em> will do the rest. So far I&rsquo;ve hooked up Pusher to Flux-style stores, then wrapped anything live-updating in a React component that observes that store. It&rsquo;s a lot more hands-on than Batman.js updates, but it has other advantages.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
