<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Roadtrip | Robert Mosolgo]]></title>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/categories/roadtrip/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-01T17:35:50-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Mosolgo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadtrip part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2013/08/20/roadtrip-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T20:28:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2013/08/20/roadtrip-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Valerie and I are on the way from Charlottesville, VA, to Carlsbad, CA. Here&rsquo;s an update from our new home!</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>Prose by Robert, photos by Valerie</em></p>

<h1>August 14</h1>

<h2>Driving to Gila Bend, AZ</h2>

<p>From Marfa, TX to Carlsbad, CA, was too long for a single day of driving, so we broke it up. The landscape can best be characterized by conversations like this one:</p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Whoa, look at those big, dry mountains way out there!&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_mountains_1.jpg" width="300" height="300"></p>

<ul>
<li><em>1 hour passes&hellip;</em></li>
<li>&ldquo;Whoa, are those mountains just ahead of us those same ones?&rdquo; &ldquo;Yep!&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_mountains_2.jpg" width="300" height="300"></p>

<ul>
<li><em>30 minutes pass&hellip;</em></li>
<li>&ldquo;Whoa, are we driving through those same mountains that we saw so far in the distance?&rdquo; &ldquo;Yeah, I think so!&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_mountains_3.jpg" width="300" height="300"></p>

<ul>
<li><em>30 minutes pass&hellip;</em></li>
<li>&ldquo;Whoa, look at those big, dry mountains way out there!&rdquo;</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_mountains_1.jpg" width="300" height="300"></p>

<ul>
<li><em>You can guess where this is going!</em></li>
</ul>


<p>Actually, there were several of such basins which were very interesting:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_new_mexico_winds_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_new_mexico_winds_2.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_new_mexico_winds_3.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>Somewhere in west Texas, we saw this strange blimp:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_blimp_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_blimp_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>Turns out, it&rsquo;s an <a href="http://www.krgv.com/news/west-texas-based-air-force-radar-blimp-crashes">unmanned craft that looks for drug planes</a>.</p>

<p>Anyways, lots of Texas, followed by a little New Mexico,</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_new_mexico_welcome.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>and then a little Arizona.</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_arizona_welcome.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>Interestingly, we found NM and AZ to be much greener than TX &mdash; lots of irrigated fields. Night fell in Arizona:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_arizona_sunset_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_arizona_sunset_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>We didn&rsquo;t have a hotel reservation, but Valerie found a great spot along the way:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_arizona_sa_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_arizona_sa_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>The <strong>Space Age Lodge</strong>. It&rsquo;s a Best Western whose first owners were supporters of NASA in its early days. The motel is decorated accordingly, with lots of space-y photos and art.</p>

<h1>August 15</h1>

<h2>Carlsbad, CA</h2>

<p>We woke up early &mdash; we were both eager to get to our new home. Along the way, we learned that there are mountains in southeastern CA:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_california_mountains_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_california_mountains_2.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_california_mountains_3.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_california_mountains_4.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>We were tired when we got here. Luckily, our belongings arrived the next day &mdash; we were rested up and excited to move in. We worked quickly &mdash; here are a few pictures of the new place during the process:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_california_apt_2.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_california_apt_3.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_california_apt_4.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p><em>The weather here is always amazing, so we eat on the porch!</em></p>

<p>Our new address is:</p>

<p>
2352 Hosp Way
<br>#247
<br>Carlsbad, CA 92008
</p>


<h2>Planning Center Online</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve started work at <a href="http://get.planningcenteronline.com">Planning Center Online</a>. I arrived at an interesting time: It&rsquo;s &ldquo;<em>free week</em>.&rdquo; All staff members have a week to invest a company project that interests them specifically. Except for occasional urgent fixes, the team is working on a handful of new features, new product ideas or other PCO-related side projects.</p>

<p>I love working here. Here are a few reasons why:</p>

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;s just like <a href="http://get.planningcenteronline.com/careers/">the video</a>.</li>
<li>All the teams usually take lunch together. I&rsquo;ve had a lot of great opportunities to meet the other guys. It&rsquo;s a lot of fun and a satisfying break from the computer screen.</li>
<li>The work environment is loaded with creative energy. A great example is <code>PiCO</code>, the <em>chat bot</em>: As with many development teams, ours has a chatroom where the team members are encouraged to socialize and collaborate on their work. Our chat room has an automated participant (a bot) named &ldquo;<code>PiCO</code>&rdquo; who moderates the discussion in several ways:

<ul>
<li>He&rsquo;s hooked up to the office coffee maker and announces <code>"FRESH POT!"</code> when the coffee is ready.</li>
<li>The front door is usually locked, but if a visitor needs to be let in, the door can be unlocked via chat room (&ldquo;<code>pico open door</code>&rdquo;).</li>
<li><code>PiCO</code> adds flavor to conversation. For example, today was someone&rsquo;s anniversary, so someone said <code>pico gif me happy anniversary</code> and <code>PiCO</code> returned this image:
<br>
<img src="/images/roadtrip_california_ha.gif" width="300" height="300">
<br>
Awesome!</li>
<li>Oh, yeah, and <code>PiCO</code> is hooked up to the web servers and bug trackers, so he can issue reminders and announcements about those :)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>(By the way, <code>PiCO</code> is a customized <a href="http://hubot.github.com/">Hubot</a>)</p>

<h1>Wrap-Up</h1>

<p>Ok, that&rsquo;s it for our travel log. Feel free to drop us a line (and thanks to those of you who already did!). Love,</p>

<p>Robert and Val</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadtrip Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2013/08/14/roadtrip-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-14T22:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2013/08/14/roadtrip-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Valerie and I are on the way from Charlottesville, VA, to Carlsbad, CA. Here&rsquo;s an update from Gila Bend, AZ!</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>Prose by Robert, photos by Valerie</em></p>

<h1>August 12</h1>

<h2>Austin, TX</h2>

<p>We started our day with a donut from <a href="http://gourdoughs.com">Gourdough&rsquo;s</a> (pronounced like &ldquo;Gordo&rsquo;s&rdquo;). It&rsquo;s a famous food truck in Austin. For some reason, Austin has loads of stationary RVs which have been converted to kitchens and serve customers through a window. Anyways, I had the <a href="http://www.gourdoughs.com/doughnuts/flying-pig/">Flying Pig</a> and Valerie had the <a href="http://www.gourdoughs.com/doughnuts/miss-shortcake/">Miss Shortcake</a>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_gourdoughs_1.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>After facing the likes of those, we were quite satisfied (/sick?), which prepared us well for our next stop. Whole Foods started in Austin and they still maintain their &ldquo;Flagship Store&rdquo;:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_wf_front.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_wf_cookies.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_wf_chocolate.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p><em>(You might notice <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stroopwafel">stroopwafels</a> on the cookie bar!)</em></p>

<p>We wandered through and ate samples, mostly :) Then, we visited 6th Street, which is the heart of Austin&rsquo;s nightlife. It was quite slow in the early afternoon, so we moved on to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barton_Springs_Pool">Barton Springs Pool</a>. We had a blast, and the pictures speak for themselves:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_pool_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_pool_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>As you can see, it&rsquo;s a pool fed by a natural spring. As you can&rsquo;t see, it was incredibly cold. I guess we &ldquo;got used to it.&rdquo; It felt good to get out, then get in, then get out, then get in&hellip;</p>

<p>Parts of the pool floor are covered in underwater grasses. Interestingly, some of the grasses were in bloom:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_pool_flower.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>Valerie raised a good question: &ldquo;Normally, plants make flowers so bugs can <del>pollenate</del> pollinate them. Why would an underwater plant bloom?&rdquo; I dont know!</p>

<p>In the afternoon, we spent time along Austin&rsquo;s South Congress Avenue. We visited some (dangerously hip) thrift stores:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_thrift_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_thrift_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>&hellip;Had a drink at the <a href="https://www.sanjosehotel.com/">Hotel San Jos&eacute;</a>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_hsj_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_hsj_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>&hellip;And then had dinner at <a href="http://www.luckyrobotrestaurant.com/">Lucky Robot</a>. We loved Lucky Robot &mdash; good food, friendly staff and very cool decor:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_lr_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_lr_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<h3>TL;DR:</h3>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_austin_sign.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<h1>August 13</h1>

<h2>Texas Hill Country / West Texas</h2>

<p>We got a (relatively, you know us) early start with our eyes set on Marfa, TX. We had hundreds of miles of Texas highway ahead of us. I&rsquo;ll share some takeaways from the day&rsquo;s drive:</p>

<ul>
<li>Texas is just <em>so big</em>. And with so much time on the road (and no viable alternative), you find yourself approaching Texas on its own terms: &ldquo;Oh, only 80 more miles, we&rsquo;re almost there!&rdquo;</li>
<li>This attitude is reinforced by billboard advertisements. We saw an add for a Hampton Inn &ldquo;just 120 miles ahead.&rdquo; Think about it: that&rsquo;s like being in Charlottesville and seeing: &ldquo;Days Inn, just ahead in Williamsburg, VA!&rdquo;</li>
<li>We did see some interesting wildlife: a badger, a roadrunner, and some armadillos (admittedly, as roadkill only :( ).</li>
<li>On Texas highways, you can go as fast as you want, but don&rsquo;t. It kills your gas mileage. And you&rsquo;d hate to run out of gas out there.</li>
<li>We washed our windshield as many times in West Texas (and New Mexico and Arizona for that matter) as I have in the rest of my life. You&rsquo;d think that with such a big state, those bugs would get out of the way.</li>
</ul>


<p>Some pictures for you:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_west_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_west_2.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_west_3.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_west_4.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<h2>Marfa, TX</h2>

<p>The main appeal of Marfa, TX (at least, for us) was <a href="http://elcosmico.com/">El Cosmico</a>, a hip(pie) hotel which offers many distinctive lodgings.</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_ec.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s the kind of place that forgoes bar soap, shampoo and conditioner in favor of a single bottle of <a href="http://www.drbronner.com/pdf/drbronner_32oz_Pep.pdf">Dr. Bronner&rsquo;s Peppermint Soap</a>. Our accomodation was the <a href="http://elcosmico.com/stay/shelter/trailers/vagabond">Vagabond</a>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_vagabond_1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_vagabond_2.jpg" width="500" height="500"></p>

<p>We had dinner in Marfa, strolled the (quiet) streets of town, and enjoyed the hammocks and reading room at El Cosmico. At last, we settled in to the Vagabond for the night. Although it wasn&rsquo;t air conditioned, we were quite comfortable because the desert gets very cold at night. We needed blankets!</p>

<p><em>We&rsquo;re in Gila Bend, AZ, now, after doing lots of driving. We should be in Carlsbad tomorrow!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadtrip part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2013/08/12/roadtrip-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-12T16:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2013/08/12/roadtrip-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Valerie and I are on the way from Charlottesville, VA, to Carlsbad, CA. Here&rsquo;s an update from Austin, TX!</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>Prose by Robert, photos by Valerie</em></p>

<h1>August 10</h1>

<h2>Panama City Beach, FL</h2>

<p>For the week of August 3-10, we were on vacation with the Wilders in Panama City Beach, FL. We had a great week of vacation before starting to head west. There were seven of us all together: Bill and Nicolien (Valerie&rsquo;s parents, and that&rsquo;s pronounced &ldquo;nick-o-LEEN&rdquo;), John Wilder, Anna Lena Wilder (that&rsquo;s &ldquo;AH-nah LAY-nah&rdquo;) and Moriah Watson (soon to be Moriah Wilder &mdash; she&rsquo;s Tom&rsquo;s fianc&eacute;e!):</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_florida_group.jpg" width="500"></p>

<h2>Panama City Beach, FL to New Orleans, LA: The Gulf Coast</h2>

<p>Our first destination was New Orleans, LA. It was about a 5-hour drive on I-10, running parallel to the Gulf Coast. On the way out, we (oh, &ldquo;I&rdquo;) had a very minor fender-bender when traffic suddenly stopped. After assessing the damage, the old man whose car I&rsquo;d hit gave us a box of donuts and wished us well for our trip:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_florida_donuts.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p><em>(He was taking leftover baked goods to his church, where they would be redistributed to the needy. He said they always have too much!)</em></p>

<p>We passed through Florida, Alabama and Mississippi (<em>&ldquo;Em-aye-ess-ess-aye-ess-ess-aye-pee-pee-aye&rdquo;</em>) before entering Louisiana.</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_alabama_welcome.jpg" width="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_mississippi_welcome.jpg" width="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_louisiana_welcome.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>We only briefly strayed from the interstate. We followed clues to some seafood restaurants (thanks, Valerie :) but found, one by one, that they had been closed. We (um, again, that&rsquo;s the royal &ldquo;we&rdquo;) also got lost and ended up at an oil refinery:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_alabama_refinery.jpg" width="500"></p>

<h2>New Orleans, LA</h2>

<p>Only three or four blocks after entering the city (in late afternoon), we saw a mid-20s-aged man in a skin-tight, short red dress and red athletic shoes. &ldquo;Wow,&rdquo; we said to one another, &ldquo;I know they say New Orleans is a wild place, but I wasn&rsquo;t expecting it so early!&rdquo; As it turned out, there was a charity &ldquo;run&rdquo; that day in which male and female participants were encouraged to wear red dresses.</p>

<p>The red dresses reappeared in the evening: the famed Bourbon Street became a red-washed frat party for adults, extending for countless blocks. Young men and women all wore red dresses of varying levels of exposure (not corresponding with gender, for better or for worse). On every block, a shop sold &ldquo;To-Go Cocktails&rdquo; which many pedestrians took advantage of. As a result, the street was filled with debris, shouts and a putrid smell.</p>

<p>Interestingly, the streets of the French Quarter are also populated by gift shops which are the New Orleans-themed equivalents of beach crap stores. Each one sold an identical collection of t-shirts, magnets, Mardi Gras beads and other paraphernalia. Many of the items aren&rsquo;t mentionable here (naturally, I considered buying some for Tom&rsquo;s bachelor party).</p>

<h1>August 11</h1>

<h2>New Orleans, LA</h2>

<p>Before departing, we hoped to get coffee and beignets from Cafe du Monde. I&rsquo;m sure many of you could have predicted what we found:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_louisiana_cafe_du_monde.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>So instead, we got breakfast elsewhere :)</p>

<h2>New Orleans, LA, to Austin, TX</h2>

<p>After breakfast, we got back on the road. Actually, before that, we applied Rain-X, which was absolutely amazing:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_louisiana_rainx.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a convert.</p>

<p>The highway in eastern Louisiana is essentially hundreds of miles of low bridges over swamps, interspersed with periods of dry land. We stopped in central LA for lunch. Valerie kindly searched for a well-reviewed restaurant which served Cajun food. She doesn&rsquo;t care for seafood, but I enjoyed it a lot. I had crayfish etouff&eacute;, which is essentially spicy crafish stew, served over rice.</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_louisiana_poches.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>When we entered Texas, we were immediately awakened to the size of the state: the first interstate exit was <em>Exit 880</em>, which means that there are almost 900 miles of I-10 in the state of Texas. Yikes!</p>

<p>The Texas welcome center was probably our favorite so far. It was built on a swamp, but they took advantage of it by creating a wildlife viewing deck:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_gator.jpg" width="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_wildlife.jpg" width="500">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_snakes.jpg" width="500"></p>

<p>Then, we spent four hours driving on flat, straight, high-speed Texas highway:</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_highway1.jpg" width="900">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_highway2.jpg" width="900">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_highway3.jpg" width="900">
<img src="/images/roadtrip_texas_highway4.jpg" width="900"></p>

<p>And at last, we checked into our hotel in Austin, TX.</p>

<p><em>We&rsquo;re in Austin now, and we&rsquo;ll let you know how it goes!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
