<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Crystal | Robert Mosolgo]]></title>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/categories/crystal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-02-04T15:33:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Mosolgo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crystal First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2015/09/27/crystal-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-27T21:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2015/09/27/crystal-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://crystal-lang.org/">Crystal programming language</a> combines Ruby-like syntax with a really powerful compiler. As a result, it&rsquo;s fun to write, fast to run, and hard to screw up!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>My Crystal experience so far:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/danott">danott</a> mentioned it in our Slack a few weeks ago</li>
<li>I read the great <a href="http://crystal-lang.org/docs/">Crystal docs</a></li>
<li>I cobbled together <a href="https://github.com/rmosolgo/crythtal">a lisp (barely)</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;d say it&rsquo;s a combination of:</p>

<ul>
<li>a more-stable-Ruby (like Elixir, but without Erlang)</li>
<li>a developer-friendly, life-embetter-ing type system (like Elm, but &hellip; not JavaScript)</li>
<li>a real compiler! (like C, but fun to read and write)</li>
</ul>


<p>Um, what else could you want?! (See last paragraph 😛)</p>

<h2>Crystal Syntax</h2>

<p>Crystal brings the best of Ruby:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Concise literals</strong>, just like Ruby (take it for granted until you use regexps in Python 🙀)</li>
<li><strong>Great OO support</strong>, classes &amp; modules just like Ruby</li>
<li><strong>Attractive syntax</strong> thanks to blocks, operator overloading and optional parens</li>
<li><strong>consistent</strong>, predictable standard library (like Ruby)</li>
</ul>


<p>Plus, some improvements over Ruby:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Method overloading</strong></li>
<li>Python-like <strong>keyword args</strong>: must have default value, may be passed as kwargs or positional args (I could go either way on this since Ruby 2.1, but it beats <code>options={}</code>)</li>
<li>More robust <strong>Proc literals</strong>, reminded me of Elixir</li>
<li>Convention: <strong><code>?</code> methods return maybe-nil types</strong>, while their counterparts raise on nil</li>
<li>First-class <strong>enums</strong> &amp; <strong>tuples</strong></li>
<li><strong>Immutable strings</strong>, like Ruby 3 will have (?)</li>
</ul>


<p>For completeness, you lose some things from Ruby:</p>

<ul>
<li>Runtime <strong>code creation</strong>, like <code>define_method</code> &amp; friends</li>
<li>Runtime <strong>code evaluation</strong>, like <code>eval</code> &amp; friends</li>
</ul>


<p>Crystal offers a powerful <strong>macro system</strong> that makes up for the loss of runtime metaprogramming. Unlike C preprossing, Crystal macros are awesome. You basically define functions which are called at compile-time, then generate code with liquid-like syntax.</p>

<h2>Crystal Typing</h2>

<h3>Inferring Types</h3>

<p>Crystal infers types from your code, so these are OK:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">my_string = "Hello World"
# String
my_hash = {key: "value", key2: "value2"}
# Hash(Symbol, String)
my_array = [1,2,3]
# Array(Int32)
</code></pre>

<p>When types mix, Crystal automatically unions them. It will ensure any usages of the variable in question are valid for both types. For example:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">my_variable = "string"
my_variable = 1
# String | Int32

# Ok, because String &amp; Int32 both implement #to_f
my_variable.to_f

# You can add runtime checks to call type-specific methods
if my_variable.is_a?(String)
  my_variable.upcase
end
</code></pre>

<p>There are some times you need to define types to help the compiler. For example, there aren&rsquo;t any values here to tell the compiler what to expect:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">some_array =  [] of Int32
# You can use custom types, too
some_hash =   {} of Symbol =&gt; SomeCustomClass
</code></pre>

<h3>Goodbye, NoMethodErrors</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re like me, you hate this:</p>

<pre><code>undefined method `whatever' for nil:NilClass
</code></pre>

<p>Something somehow became nil. 😢</p>

<p>Instead, Crystal reads your code, and if there&rsquo;s somewhere a value could be nil, it throws a compile error:</p>

<pre><code>in ./src/lisp/binding.cr:55: undefined method 'find_owner' for Nil

      @parent.find_owner(key)
              ^~~~~~~~~~
</code></pre>

<p>You have two options:</p>

<ul>
<li>Add an explicit not-nil check (<code>if object.is_a?(String) ...</code>) so the compiler knows it will be safe</li>
<li>Refactor so the value won&rsquo;t be nil</li>
</ul>


<p>Of course, the first one seems better at the start, but I hope to get better at the second one 😁.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s Missing?</h2>

<p>Crystal really shows its youth. Its shortcomings all fall in that vein:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Poorly documented</strong>, which isn&rsquo;t so bad if you&rsquo;re coming from Ruby</li>
<li><strong>Few projects</strong> out there (I think the <a href="http://crystalshards.herokuapp.com/">package repository is a free Heroku app</a>)</li>
<li>Standard library has <strong>some kinks</strong>, they say it is still changing</li>
</ul>


<p>One example of a standard library kink is the handling of <code>break</code>, <code>next</code> and <code>return</code> in blocks. If you want to exit a block early, you have to choose one of those three. The problem is that, to choose the right one, you have to know whether the method captures the block into a proc or simply yields values to it. It&rsquo;s a drag to have to know a method&rsquo;s implementation to call it! (IRL, I didn&rsquo;t run into this and I suspect it would be easy enough to work around it.)</p>

<h2>Now What?</h2>

<p>I really liked Crystal and I hope I can work with it more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
