<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Conferences | Robert Mosolgo]]></title>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/categories/conferences/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-03-28T10:14:23-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Mosolgo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trip Report: Balkan Ruby 2018]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2018/06/14/trip-report-balkan-ruby-2018/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-14T15:02:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2018/06/14/trip-report-balkan-ruby-2018</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This May, I had the opportunity to attend <a href="https://balkanruby.com/">Balkan Ruby</a> and present on my work with <a href="https://github.com/rmosolgo/graphql-ruby">graphql-ruby</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here are a few thoughts about the trip.</p>

<h2>The Conference</h2>

<p>Balkan Ruby was a big hit. Personally, some of my favorites were:</p>

<ul>
<li>Zach Holman&rsquo;s opening talk about datetimes and timezones (which became a <a href="https://zachholman.com/talk/utc-is-enough-for-everyone-right">blog post</a> and inspired a <a href="https://github.com/rmosolgo/graphql-ruby/pull/1566">GraphQL-Ruby ISO8601 scalar type</a>)</li>
<li>Sameer Deshmukh&rsquo;s presentation about various <a href="https://github.com/sciruby">SciRuby</a> projects</li>
<li>Marko Bogdanović&rsquo;s talk about <a href="https://rubybench.org/">RubyBench</a>, which was a really cool project and made me want something like it for GraphQL-Ruby.</li>
</ul>


<p>One of my favorite parts of the conference was the code challenges set up by <a href="">Receipt Bank</a>, one of the sponsors.</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/challenge.png" width="500"></p>

<p>Every few hours, a new, wacky challenge would go live. Although I didn&rsquo;t do well on them, I enjoyed working with a few new friends on different solutions, and seeing the creative things that other attendees submitted!</p>

<h2>The City</h2>

<p>Sofia was <strong>great</strong>. A beautiful city with interesting architecture, tons of trees and tasty food.</p>

<p>The Nevski Cathedral was built in the early 1900s to celebrate Russia&rsquo;s liberation of Bulgaria from the Ottomans:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/nevski.png" width="500"></p>

<p>Inside, a mural of Abraham and Isaac:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/abraham.png" width="500"></p>

<p>And St. Cyril and St. Methodius, creators of the Cyrillic alphabet, who are quite popular around here:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/saints.png" width="500"></p>

<p>I really enjoyed the different cathedrals. There&rsquo;s something cool about the different instructive artwork and &ldquo;sacred&rdquo; feeling of a beautiful building with incense burning. I wonder if modern American churches could do more to engage all of our senses.</p>

<p>Also, a bit of Soviet history found in a nearby park:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/soviet.png" width="500"></p>

<p>And here, some recently excavated Roman ruins, and the one remaining Turkish mosque downtown:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/ruins.png" width="500"></p>

<p>The mosque was right beside ruins of an old bathhouse. Apparently that&rsquo;s why Sofia was founded here &ndash; there were hot springs on the road between Rome and Constantinople, so the Romans set up camp (and called it Serdica).</p>

<p>And a fairly typical meal during my time there, a <em>shopska</em> salad (veggies with cheese, oil, and vinegar):</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/food.png" width="500"></p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say enough good things about the local dairy products. The cheese was soft and fresh and the yogurt was tart and refreshing.</p>

<h2>The Organizers</h2>

<p>My favorite part about programming conferences is meeting the smart, caring folks who make them possible, and Balkan Ruby was no exception.</p>

<p>The two main organizers, <a href="https://twitter.com/gsamokovarov">Genadi</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/vestimir">Vestimir</a> were fantastic hosts (and experienced, since they got their start with Euruko a few years back). Besides that, I really enjoyed meeting the volunteers and learning a bit about life in Sofia.</p>

<p>One thing that stood out to me was the tradition behind the local liquor, rakia. It turns out that many families make it themselves, despite a law against owning stills. I&rsquo;ve been reading that peach wine was the traditional alcoholic drink for the earliest European arrivals to my area, so I decided to give it a shot this summer!</p>

<p>A big bonus was when Vestimir played trail guide for our hike up the nearby mountain, Mt. Vitosha. It turned out to be a gray day, but we had a blast anyways.</p>

<p>Some pictures of the trail:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/trail1.png" width="500"></p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/trail2.png" width="500"></p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/trail3.png" width="500"></p>

<p>Beautiful! But you could say were were <em>a bit</em> underdressed XD</p>

<p>At the summit, we were happy to find a lodge where some food was served.</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/hut.png" width="500"></p>

<p>Some traditional bean soup, bread, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ljutenica">lyutenitsa</a>, cheese tea, and rakia never tasted so good.</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/snack.png" width="500"></p>

<p>Enjoying a rest:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/group.png" width="500"></p>

<p>(Left-to-right: Andreas, Nynne, Sameer, Me and Vestimir)</p>

<p>And, pleasantly, we caught a nice view of Sofia on the way back down:</p>

<p><img src="/images/balkan_ruby_2018/overlook.png" width="500"></p>

<p>(You can even see the Nevski cathedral if you look closely!)</p>

<h2>Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>Balkan Ruby was a big hit on all fronts: great people, great city, great technical content. Especially as a dairy lover, I&rsquo;ll take the next chance I get to go back! And I loved making some new friends, who I hope to see at future Ruby events.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trip Report: RubyConf Colombia 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2016/09/04/trip-report-rubyconf-colombia-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-04T22:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2016/09/04/trip-report-rubyconf-colombia-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just got back from <a href="http://rubyconf.co">RubyConf Colombia</a>. The content was great, the community was great, and the venue was great!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Content</h2>

<p>This was a single-track conference, but there were no dud talks! I prefer code-driven talks, and for that reason, these were a few of my favorites:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/davidpelaez">David Pelaez</a> demoed some functional concepts in Ruby, including <code>Right</code> and <code>Left</code> (?? name) and <code>None</code> objects.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/orendon">Oscar Rendon</a> described an approach to combining business rules which allows you to simplify conditional branching and reuse code more effectively.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/apotonick">Nick Sutterer</a> shared some insights into busting up &ldquo;god objects&rdquo; into more specialized, context-specific units of code.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/sarcilav">Sebastian Arcila-Valensuela</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/febuiles">Frederico Builes</a> gave my favorite non-code talk. They told a funny story of making tradeoffs while working on a tough problem: building a human-friendly path from a disjoint set of points.</li>
</ul>


<p>I presented <a href="/talks">&ldquo;Data Fetching with GraphQL and ActionCable&rdquo;</a> while I was there, and I was happy with how it went.</p>

<h2>The Community</h2>

<p>My favorite part of this event was getting to know the local Ruby community. In fact, I should say &ldquo;software development community&rdquo;, as many attendees were not full-time Ruby developers.</p>

<p>Many things were familiar to me: these folks are building interesting projects (like <a href="https://www.wesura.com/">Wesura</a>, peer-to-peer insurance, and <a href="https://vlip.co/">Vlip</a>, a mobile payment platform). They&rsquo;re excited about doing great work and learning new things. Also, there&rsquo;s a big focus on training and education: many attendees were students at local universities or participants in web dev bootcamps.</p>

<p>Other things were different. I saw many more female attendees at this conference than others. I know that this was a goal for the organizers, bravo to them for succeeding! Also, the community is relatively new. RubyConf Colombia is the only Ruby conference in Spanish-speaking Latin America (the other is in Brazil), and it requires <strong>a lot</strong> of work to plan and execute, because there isn&rsquo;t so much momentum in place. For example, there&rsquo;s not a culture of companies sending their employees to conferences, so many attendees paid out of pocket.</p>

<p>I also realized something I take for granted: as a native English speaker, basically <em>all</em> technical information is available in my mother tongue, no matter where in the world it came from. What a blessing! It makes me think how valuable the translation service must have been for some native Spanish speakers. Of course, it was hugely valuable to me too &ndash; I would have been lost without it during the Spanish-language talks!</p>

<h2>The Venue</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.elteatrico.co/">El Teatrico</a> was a great spot for this event. We were close to max capacity, and that gave the conference a very intimate feeling. During breaks, you couldn&rsquo;t help but start a conversation with your neighbor.</p>

<p>Besides that, the translation was <em>amazing</em>! There were two guys taking turns, and they did a great job keeping up with the talks and translating technical vocabulary. I felt like I understood almost 100% of the Spanish-language talks.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed Medellin, too. It checked all the boxes for me: great environment, great people and great food!</p>

<h2>Photos</h2>

<p><img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/organizers.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>(via <a href="https://twitter.com/gigo6000/status/772228777367724032">@gigo6000 on Twitter</a>)</p>

<p><img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/talk_1.jpg" width="300">
<img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/el_teatrico_2.jpg" width="300">
<img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/el_teatrico_1.jpg" width="200">
<img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/medellin_1.jpg" width="200">
<img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/medellin_2.jpg" width="200">
<img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/landscape_1.jpg" width="200">
<img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/medellin_3.jpg" width="200">
<img src="/images/rubyconf_co_2016/aguardiente.jpg" width="200"></p>

<h2>In Summary</h2>

<p>This was a wonderful trip! I loved making some new friends and visiting this fantastic city. I really appreciate the work of the organizers, and that their primary goal is really to benefit their community. I&rsquo;m excited to see what next year holds for them!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
