<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Angular.js | Robert Mosolgo]]></title>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/categories/angular-dot-js/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-09-02T11:30:46-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Mosolgo]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Render Scope in AngularJS and Batman.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2014/08/10/render-scope-in-angular-dot-js-and-batman-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-10T18:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2014/08/10/render-scope-in-angular-dot-js-and-batman-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://batmanjs.org">Batman.js</a> and <a href="http://angularjs.org">AngularJS</a> both create hierarchical view scopes, but their implementations are very different.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>(please forgive my inconsistent rendering of AngularJS/Angular/Angular.js/angular, I don&rsquo;t know which one is right!)</em></p>

<p>In batman.js and Angular, there is a view scope <em>hierarchy</em> which mirrors the DOM. In this heirarchy, objects may:</p>

<ul>
<li>add values into the render scope</li>
<li>access <em>their own</em> values</li>
<li>belong to a <em>parent object</em></li>
<li>access values from <em>their parents</em></li>
<li>have <em>child objects</em> of their own</li>
</ul>


<p>Consider a page like this:</p>

<p><a href="/images/batmanjs_nested_views.png"><img src="/images/batmanjs_nested_views.png" alt="Batman.js view hierarchy" /></a></p>

<p>The <code>HouseholdView</code> has many child views. The <code>PersonView</code>s belong to their parent, <code>HouseholdView</code>. They may access values from <code>HouseholdView</code> (such as the shared <code>householdName</code>).</p>

<p><em>Note: The batman.js view hierarchy includes a few other objects as well &ndash; see below.</em></p>

<h1>Finding Values in the Hierarchy</h1>

<p>To answer the question &ldquo;how can child views access data from their parents&rdquo;, Batman.js and Angular take different approaches.</p>

<h3>$scope &amp; Prototypal Inheritance</h3>

<p>In Angular, data bindings are evaluated against a <strong>magical <code>$scope</code> object</strong>. The scope object has key-value pairs which correspond to values in the data bindings. When <code>$scope</code>s are created, Angular massages (tampers with?) the prototypal inheritance chain so that a child scope&rsquo;s prototype <em>is</em> its parent scope.</p>

<p>(Usually, an object&rsquo;s prototype is another &ldquo;pristine&rdquo; object of its same type. It&rsquo;s generally treated as the &ldquo;perfect instance&rdquo; of the type. Other instances delegate to the prototype for properties that aren&rsquo;t defined explicitly on themselves.)</p>

<p>In this case, a child <code>$scope</code>&rsquo;s prototype is not a &ldquo;pristine instance&rdquo;, but instead it&rsquo;s the parent <code>$scope</code> object. That way, if a value isn&rsquo;t found in a child scope, it is looked up in the prototype chain. This is <strong>brilliant</strong>. Angular delegates value lookup to built-in JavaScript features. (There is one gotcha described below.)</p>

<p>When a parent <code>$scope</code> has many children, all children have the same parent <code>$scope</code> object as their prototype.</p>

<h3>Batman.View &amp; View::lookupKeypath</h3>

<p>Batman.js builds a <strong>tree of <code>Batman.View</code> objects</strong>. The root of the tree is called the <code>LayoutView</code> and it is created automatically by batman.js. Each view keeps track of its children in its <code>subviews</code>, which is a <code>Batman.Set</code> containing views that are rendered inside it. Each view also keeps track of its <code>superview</code>, which is its parent <code>Batman.View</code>.</p>

<p>To evaluate data bindings, batman.js uses <code>lookupKeypath</code> on the view in question. This function climbs the &ldquo;view hierarchy&rdquo;, which actually includes a few extra objects:</p>

<ul>
<li>The <code>Batman.Controller</code> instance which rendered the view</li>
<li><code>Batman.currentApp</code>, which is the <code>Batman.App</code> subclass that you defined (the clas, not an instance)</li>
<li><code>Batman.container</code>, which is usually <code>window</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Here&rsquo;s the whole view hierarchy from the previous example:</p>

<p><a href="/images/batmanjs_nested_views_whole_tree.png"><img src="/images/batmanjs_nested_views_whole_tree.png" alt="The whole batman.js view hierarchy" /></a></p>

<p>Since <code>Batman.currentApp</code> is in the view hierarchy, any <code>@classAccessor</code>s you define there are accessible in view bindings, akin to global scope in JavaScript.</p>

<h1>Automatically-Created Scopes</h1>

<p>In batman.js and Angular, there are data bindings that create child scopes of their own. For example, <code>ng-repeat</code> and <code>data-foreach</code> both create a collection of child scopes with the same parent.</p>

<p>Angular does this by creating many child <code>$scopes</code> with the same parent <code>$scope</code> as their prototype.</p>

<p>Batman.js does this by automatically adding nodes to the view hierarchy. One downside of batman.js is that creating lots and lots of new views is CPU-intensive. I don&rsquo;t know whether the same is true for creating <code>$scope</code>s.</p>

<h1>How Does It Know Which Scope to Bind To?</h1>

<p>When I was reading about <code>$scope</code>, I learned that some new Angular users hit a snag when they try to set values on a <em>parent scope</em> from within a <em>child scope</em>. As JavaScript should, it updates the child <code>$scope</code> with the new value, not the parent <code>$scope</code>, which is the child&rsquo;s prototype.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how prototypal inheritance works: It looks up missing values on the prototype, but it sets <em>new</em> values on the instance. Then, it stops &ldquo;falling back&rdquo; to the prototype for the property that was set on the instance.</p>

<p>To work around this, it&rsquo;s recommended to &ldquo;always use a <code>.</code> in your <code>ng-model</code>s&rdquo;. (<code>ng-model</code> is a binding that creates a child scope.)</p>

<p>Batman.js doesn&rsquo;t have this problem because, when uses <code>lookupKeypath</code>, it remembers which <code>View</code> object was the target for that keypath, then updates <em>that object</em> whenever the keypath changes.</p>

<p>However, Batman.js is prone to a different gotcha. If you leave an accessor unset (ie, returns <code>undefined</code>), then set it <em>after</em> a view has rendered, it&rsquo;s possible that <code>View::lookupKeypath</code> won&rsquo;t find it correctly. To avoid this, set defaults (or <code>null</code>) before bindings are evaluated:</p>

<ul>
<li>before <code>@render</code> in controller actions</li>
<li>in the <code>constructor</code> for view instances</li>
</ul>


<p>Or, make sure <code>@accessor</code>s return <code>null</code> instead of <code>undefined</code>.</p>

<p>Batman.js treats <code>undefined</code> as the signal that an object doesn&rsquo;t have an accessor for a keypath, so be careful when setting keys <code>undefined</code>!</p>

<h1>How Does It Know When to Update the DOM?</h1>

<p>When these scope objects (<code>View</code> or <code>$scope</code>) change, the framework must update the DOM accordingly.</p>

<p>Angular has a &ldquo;digest cycle&rdquo; where it checks for changes in the <code>$scope</code> since last run, then updates the DOM if necessary. It automatically tracks any values that are put into templates. You can also watch other keys on <code>$scope</code> with <code>$scope.$watch</code>. If you modify <code>$scope</code> from <em>outside</em> Angular.js code, you must manually trigger the digest cycle with <code>$scope.$apply</code>.</p>

<p><code>Batman.View</code> uses the <a href="http://rmosolgo.github.io/blog/2014/04/20/automatic-source-tracking-in-batman-dot-js/"><code>Batman.Property</code></a> system to automatically track dependencies and changes. Any keypath that is passed to a <code>data-</code> binding is automatically observed. DOM updates are triggered when:</p>

<ul>
<li>A keypath is updated with <code>set</code>. Doesn&rsquo;t matter whether it&rsquo;s inside batman.js code or inside an AJAX callback &ndash; batman.js will recognize the update either way.</li>
<li>A property&rsquo;s dependencies change. When you declare a computed property with <code>@accessor</code> and bind it to a view, the view will update the DOM whenever that property&rsquo;s dependencies cause it to change.</li>
</ul>


<p>(In fact, those two cases are the heart of observability in batman.js: assign a value with <code>set</code> or delegate to batman.js&rsquo;s source tracking.)</p>

<p>To force an update, use <code>set</code> to update a bound property or one of its dependencies.</p>

<h1>Other Random Points</h1>

<ul>
<li>Angular&rsquo;s &ldquo;evalute an expression&rdquo; is like batman.js&rsquo;s &ldquo;lookup a keypath&rdquo;</li>
<li><code>Batman.View::propagateToSubviews</code> is like <code>$scope.$broadcast</code>: it sends messages down the view tree.</li>
<li>As of batman.js almost-v0.17, there is no analog for <code>$scope.$emit</code> (which sends events <em>up</em> the view chain)</li>
<li>batman.js exports global function <code>$context($0)</code> which is just like <code>angular.element($0).scope()</code> (where <code>$0</code> is the highlighted element in the Chrome inspector).</li>
</ul>


<h1>My Opinion</h1>

<p>I think Angular&rsquo;s <code>$scope</code> is brilliant. I imagine it&rsquo;s performant as well, although I don&rsquo;t know (and I&rsquo;m currently writing without internet access). It introduces few gotchas. In general, it seems like it Just Works<sup>TM</sup>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m in the market to improve the performance of <code>Batman.View</code>, but I&rsquo;m not sure I can take anything from <code>$scope</code>. All of batman.js depends on playing by the observability rules. I don&rsquo;t see any way I can get native JS prototypal inheritance to participate in that.</p>

<p>I also like sticking with the &ldquo;It&rsquo;s just batman.js&rdquo; in the view layer. If you can write good <code>@accessor</code>s, then you&rsquo;ve mastered <code>Batman.View</code>, too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
